Hello, and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're just going to go
over what a brief introduction of
chemical reaction is what we're
going to be learning about next.
Now, what does it mean
by chemical reaction?
Well, this is the entire purpose
of taking chemistry is trying to
understand what happens when we have
different chemicals that react together.
This is something that's found
all throughout your entire
life, everywhere around you.
So in the background here, I have
images of all kinds of different
processes that are stuff you
probably do every single day.
So for example, digestion, right?
We all love to eat and
we eat every single day.
That process is what every time you
eat something, all those different
chemicals that you are ingesting into
your body get broken down into thousands
of individual molecules that get used
for all their different resources.
to help you live and to be able to do
all the metabolic activities that you do
every day, just by moving and breathing.
So you are doing millions and trillions
of reaction every single second.
Other things that we do, right?
Right now you're watching this
video on a laptop or a phone.
The batteries in your device
are a chemical reaction.
As the chemicals get excited,
they transfer electrons
to help power your device.
And to allow it to be going, if
you had to drive to school, right?
And you used a normal gas powered car,
you went that you use a combustion
reaction where the gasoline burned
and that helped propel your car.
Same thing.
If you're like, Oh, I
drive an electric car.
Well, go back to batteries.
And it was, it's the same
idea of powering your vehicle.
Um, if you have, let's say a bunch
of stuff like laying around in your
backyard and the rusting and the
sun and the, and the atmosphere.
And you see that metal and it's
starting to turn different colors.
Well, that is another example, right?
We just went through a pandemic where
it was pretty much told like a wash
your hands every, every second you
get to try to eliminate exposure
to different germs and something
you should do any every day anyway.
Why do you do that?
Well, putting soap on your hands helps
destroy bacterial cell walls to help stop
them from reproducing helps destroy them.
Um, if you're someone that loves cooking
or baking or creating things in your own
kitchen, All of these are also reactions.
You're over the age of 21 in the U.
S.
and you love to drink on the
weekends, potentially, all that
process, how is it all made?
Fermentation, right?
The creation of alcohol is something
that's a common process, or just
fermentation of making like, let's
say, cheeses, or bread, or different
vinegars, and different things like that.
They're also all made using microorganisms
to create a lot of the other different
food sources we use on a regular day.
So chemical reactions are everywhere.
And since the very beginning of chemistry,
one of the things that I say in a lot of
my videos as well, what's the thing that
we're really doing and it's trying to
understand is how and why matter changes.
And that's the idea of trying to
understand this, this next chapter
with the videos is seeing how
exactly do we see these reactions
all over all over the place.
Right, if you have the unfortune of
driving a car that's, you know, a little
worse for wear, and you see that, hey,
it's starting to rust a little bit,
you know, it still runs great, but
it's starting to fall apart a little
bit, that is a chemical reaction.
If you ever see money sitting on
the sidewalk and it's been there
for a really long time, you'll
see that oxidation layer on it.
That is another chemical reaction,
trying to, if you have fruit or if it's
been sitting maybe on your counter for
a little too long, it starts turning
black, still tastes sort of okay.
It tastes a little different.
Now, why is that?
Well, once again, it's reactions at work.
So we're going to be really looking
and trying to dive into these
and try to understand exactly
what it is that we're seeing.
Now, with all these chemical reactions,
all are surrounded via chemical.
Right.
There was physical changes, which was just
kind of changing the form of something
going from like a solid, a liquid to a
gas, maybe a changing, maybe breaking
it or tearing it or doing different
changes of the shape, chemical changes
when the molecules they rearrange
and create something completely new.
Right.
So, and how can you see these?
Well, some of them are color changes.
Right.
If you are cooking at home and let's
say you have a meat on the grill, right?
Originally, it's like a pink
red color, but then it starts
browning at the aroma change, the
smell changes, the colors change.
This is a chemical reaction
that's right in front of you.
If you have a precipitation occur, let's
say a solid is all of a sudden made.
Where you mix two liquids
together and then all of a
sudden a solid comes out of it.
Like, how is that even possible?
Well, due to the solubility rules of
different ionic compounds, you could
actually be making precipitation,
which we will be covering as
well in videos in this series.
Now, if there's a gas that comes up,
right, if one of the diatomic gases
is created, or if you have all these
different CO2 or ammonia, or all these
different aromas that come off as
well, or odors, these are gases, right?
If you can, all of a sudden those
didn't smell like anything, all of a
sudden start smelling, all of a sudden
you have a chemical reaction, right?
If there's an odor that comes out
of nowhere in your house, it's like,
well, where's that coming from?
Well, that's a chemical reaction
that is occurring somewhere.
If you have light that is being created,
electromagnetic radiation, where
electrons are getting excited, they're
relaxing down and we can see that
light that comes from the electrons.
That is another process or heat with
thermochemistry, where all of a sudden
something can absorb a bunch of energy.
It can change how the temperatures, how
it behaves, how we can actually see it.
Maybe it will get colder, right,
through heat packs or cold packs.
These are all different
types of chemical reactions.
Um, so we're going to be really
looking at this picture and
trying to get a little idea.
So before we do that, let's take a
look at some different demonstrations.
Chemical reactions can be some
of the coolest looking reactions
that we can ever see and they can
be some of the silliest ones too.
So for this one, I thought this was
a really cool color change where it
goes from blue to clear and you're
going to see it turn back to blue.
So this is an iodine.
Block reaction, where it keeps
changing and circulating, oscillating
colors over and over and over again.
So this is one of those things
where there's a color change.
It was clear, it went from to gold,
then to blue, and it kept oscillating.
This is a chemical change.
Another example that you might have
seen in class potentially could have
also been in the form of fire, right?
One of the things that I love to show
to my students when we're learning
about electrons and how they get excited
is how fire can essentially show how
light can be emitted differently.
Right.
So all right here, there's a bunch of
different salts that are ionic compounds
that if they absorb a ton of their energy
through thermochemistry, you can see
they all have different colors to them.
And it's all about the
different energetics, right?
As these things are transforming and
changing their molecules and atoms are
rearranging into different structures.
We can actually see how they
could actually exude and
exhibit light as a result.
So this is some of the examples that
you can see in your chemistry course.
Now, what, is this as simple as, oh, can I
just watch all these different test tubes?
Sometimes it is.
You're just mixing things together
and seeing what you observe.
When you're observing a chemical
reaction, you write down
everything you are observing.
You put screw sheeting detail
into what you're doing.
Now, this goes the same for
why is a skill so important.
Many people that take my courses are
health science majors, meaning that you're
going to be taking care of patients.
Maybe you're someone who just wants
to be a scientist, or an engineer,
or a physicist, or a chemist,
or a biologist, but your entire
career is based on observation.
So you need to be able to
write down what you're seeing.
You also need to be able to scientifically
explain what you're seeing as well.
So how exactly can that work?
Well, if you're trying to look at a
chemical equation, the way that we show
this is we have the reactants and the
products, meaning the reactants are
what you start with in a reaction, the
products are what you are creating.
Now the way that we convey these
is typically that you will see a
bunch of chemicals written down
with an arrow pointing towards
the products, illustrating
exactly what it is you are making.
Reaction.
And the way to kind of think of this
is it's very similar to if you're
cooking at home, where if you're
trying to follow a recipe and you are
baking, well you could have all your
ingredients that you're starting off with.
Your flour, your sugar,
your milk, your eggs.
These are your reactants.
You can mix them all together to create a
cake, bread, or something completely new.
So you're yielding or creating these.
So this is what we're going to
be learning how to do, is how to
balance these chemical reactions.
How to predict them.
And this is going to be something
that's going to be coming up
shortly for the weeks to come.
So we will try to make
this a big component.
Now when we are illustrating all these
different substances, not only are we
producing or yielding things, But we're
going to be using familiar symbols to
illustrate our phase changes as well.
Whether it's a solid, a liquid, or a gas,
you will see these written in parentheses
next to your substance to illustrate,
okay, this is the phase that's occurring.
Because if you think about it,
intermolecular forces, which is stuff
that's been talked about a lot, help pull
these chemicals together to help them
start to react and start to change and
to actually cause a big impact on this.
So this is something that you need to be
able to illustrate exactly what it is that
you saw, what phase was it in, because it
changes exactly how you're conveying that
information from one person to the other.
Now, if you have AQ, what is that?
Well, if you don't remember, aqueous
means that it's dissolved in water.
So thinking ion dipole interaction,
it was soluble, it broke apart, it's
in water, which is a big component,
sometimes the water participates in the
reaction, and you need to show that.
If you see a triangle written, think
delta T, back to thermochemistry,
this is all about heat is being used.
So delta means, or triangle, so they're
all little important little tidbits that
we'll see in these different reactions.
Now, most of these are
written as chemical equations.
And this is a skill that you need to
know in order to master chemistry.
It takes a lot of practice to be able
to get comfortable using these, and
it's something that you will get a
lot of experience doing as you go
through dozens and hundreds of problems
trying to really get a hold of this.
But this is a simple concept if
you think about it, is essentially
whatever I put into the reaction
is what is going to be coming out.
So meaning that if I have, on the left
hand side, I have two atoms of hydrogen
are combining with two atoms of oxygen.
The one thing that you notice is
that it's not equal on both sides.
Now that's breaking a rule, isn't it?
If you remember, there was conservation
of mass, which chemical reactions
and what they show is that whatever
matter goes into the reaction.
Remember, matter or mass cannot
be created nor destroyed the
fundamental law of our world.
So essentially, if we go put
whatever is in, we need to
balance the chemical equation.
And the way that we will do that is by
using coefficients in order to do that.
So when you see chemical reactions,
you will see numbers written in
front of them, just like this,
where okay, in this reaction.
I wanted to balance both sides, so
what you see is, if you do 2 times 2
hydrogens, that means you have a total
of 4, right, and that's combining
with 2 oxygens, and it's creating 2
water molecules, but total, right,
we have 4 hydrogens and 2 oxygens.
You can, um, essentially, uh,
carry through the mathematics here.
Just to illustrate exactly how this works
and what, how you're going to be doing
this in homework is in every problem You
always got to make sure it's balanced.
Do not always expect that it is It's
something that you need to double
check for yourself and get comfortable
doing so if we were to look at this
Let's say I had the following reaction.
How do we how exactly does this work?
Well, I have a two in front of sodium
hydroxide up here How that's gonna
actually work is the 2 gets distributed
to each element that's in this formula.
So that means you have 2 sodiums,
2 oxygens, and 2 hydrogens.
Now that doesn't mean you're gonna put
little subscripts next to all these,
it just tells you you have 2 sodium
hydroxide compounds that are reacting with
1 magnesium nitrate compound to create 2
sodium nitrates and 1 magnesium hydroxide.
These represent how many
moles of a compound you have
within your chemical formula.
So you can kind of get an idea,
it's like, oh, oh no, it's going
to come back to moles as well.
It tells you exactly what
it is that you're seeing.
Okay.
So this is the basic idea of how
we're going to be looking at chemical
reactions, which we'll eventually
get into how you can actually balance
and write out these little equations.
So we will be going into our next
or my next video in this series,
how to balance chemical equations.
Using this how to guide of
going through them and trying to
practice it as much as possible.
This is going to be a skill that's going
to be used in, in essentially introductory
chemistry and general chemistry.
And if you are a chemistry or biology
major, it's something that you will see
throughout your entire scientific studies.
So practice it, master it,
and fully understand it, okay?
So thank you so much for listening.
I hope this video helped you get a
basic idea of chemical reactions.
And thank you so much for
watching and listening.
I hope to see you all later.
Bye now.